

# Oleksii Shevtsov, PhD

Teleskopgatan 18, 41557 Göteborg +46 76 011 50 17 alex.shevtsov1988@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/oleksii-shevtsov/

# PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Passionate self-driven problem solver and researcher with a background in theoretical physics. More than 3 years hands-on industry experience and more than 9 years in academic research setting. Broad experience in solving and managing complex tasks as demonstrated by 14 successfully completed research and industry projects. Strong analytical skills and proficiency in several programming languages: C++ (9 years), Python (11 years), JavaScript (4 years), and Elixir (1.5 years). Have been involved in solving some of the most demaning problems in automotive and aviation industries. Implemented software tools which allowed to perform sophisticated scientific calculations, analysis, and visualization resulting in 16 publications in recognized peer-reviewed journals.

## WORK EXPERIENCE

## Software Application Developer (Level 4)

Oct. 2021 - Now

Jeppesen Systems AB (A Boeing Company), Göteborg, Sweden

- Have been taking part in the project on implementing a system for real-time tracking and adjustment of the monthly schedule for the crew members of one of the biggest cargo carriers in the world.
- Have worked closely with the customer to refine, analyze, and architect technical solutions based on the business requirements.
- Work as a team lead responsible for delivering the software module for automated calculation of adjustments to the crew member monthly pay, based on the schedule changes.
- Communicate with other teams and stakeholders to make sure that dependencies and integration points with external systems are satisfied.

#### Software Application Developer (Level 3)

Jan. 2020 – Oct. 2021

Jeppesen Systems AB (A Boeing Company), Göteborg, Sweden

- Have played a leading role in the team of developers implementing contractual agreement rules
  concerning monthly payments of the crew members, based on the schedule changes which occurred
  during the operations.
- Have got promoted to the senior developer level based on the responsibility taken and the performace demonstrated during the coarse of the project. Have become responsible for leading the team working on the payments module.
- Won a global 3-day hackathon competition (in a team of 3) among company offices worldwide for implementing, as a proof-of-concept, a containerized version of the development environment accessible as a cloud SaaS solution. My role was to implement a web-based UI (with React framework), which used websocket connection and an HTML VNC client to create a user session and connect to the development environment in the web browser.

## Embedded Software Engineer (consultant)

Aug. 2018 – Jan. 2020

Smart Eye AB, Göteborg, Sweden

- Was a part of an agile team of developers and researchers working on the software solutions for active driver assistance systems (ADAS) developed for some of the biggest car OEMs worldwide.
- Developed an algorithm for detection of a driver's eye pupil center for the case when the pupil is seen as bright (much harder than the dark pupil case). It allowed to substantially decrease the average spread and error in gaze tracking accuracy.
- Added support for megapixel cameras (as opposed to lower-resolution ones used in earlier projects) to the main library and its supporting Python tools.
- Completed a project on redesign and implementation of an interactive UI-based application using Python and its bindings with the Qt5 framework. It is used to support dynamic camera functionality in the main library, needed when the IR camera is located on the steering wheel column and can change its position.
- Made multiple contributions to the automated software testing infrastructure.

#### **Embedded Software Engineer**

Aug. 2018 – Jan. 2020

AFRY AB (previously ÅF AB), Göteborg, Sweden

- Took part in the in-house project related to virtual reality (VR) architectural visualization. Working closely with the group of graphics designers and architects, contributed to the project by programming user interaction support within a futuristic city scenery, using C# and Unity engine (see short demo here). The visualization was developed for Oculus Rift VR kit.
- In September 2018 started an assignment as embedded software engineer consultant at Smart Eye AB.

#### Postdoctoral Researcher

Oct. 2015 – Jun. 2018

Northwestern University, Evanston IL, United States

- Led 2 research projects on transport properties of electrons under the surface of superfluid <sup>3</sup>He, resulting in 2 publications in the international peer-review journals.
- Developed C++ code for parallel computations on a university computer cluster.
- Participated in two international conferences and gave two invited and one contributed talk.
- Maintained active collaboration with the group of Prof. M. Fogelström from Chalmers University.

#### Postdoctoral Researcher

 $Jan.\ 2013-Oct.\ 2015$ 

Chalmers Tekniska Högskola, Göteborg, Sweden

- Led a research project on superconducting devices sponsored by the Swedish Research Council. As a result, two scientific papers were published and the results presented at multiple international conferences.
- Co-supervised two PhD candidates resulting in 5 collaborative scientific publications and 4 completed projects. Both candidates successfully graduated.
- Developed a short course of lectures for PhD students and postdocs in the lab.

#### **Doctoral Researcher**

Nov. 2009 - Oct. 2012

Commissariat à l'Energie Atomique et aux Energies Alternatives (CEA), Grenoble, France

- Responsible for 3 projects on non-equilibrium transport properties of multiterminal nanodevices and graphene sponsored by the French CFR grant, under supervision of Dr. Xavier Waintal.
- Developed numerical code written in Python for parallel computations on the local computer cluster resulting in 5 scientific publications and a PhD thesis. Maintained a successful collaboration with other group members and a research group in Lyon.

## **EDUCATION**

#### PhD in Nanophysics

Nov. 2009 – Nov. 2012

Université Grenoble Alpes, Grenoble France

Thesis title: "Contribution to the theory of quantum transport: graphene-based topological insulator and finite-frequency phenomena"

Thesis advisor: Dr. Xavier Waintal (CEA Grenoble)

#### Master in Theoretical Physics

Sep. 2008 – Sep. 2009

Taras Shevchenko National University of Kyiv, Kyiv Ukraine

Summa Cum Laude. Research advisor: Dr. Yuriy Klymenko (National Academy of Sciences of Ukraine)

### **Bachelor** in Theoretical Physics

Sep. 2004 – Sep. 2008

Taras Shevchenko National University of Kyiv, Kyiv Ukraine

Summa Cum Laude. Research advisor: Dr. Yuriy Klymenko (National Academy of Sciences of Ukraine)

#### E-Learning Courses:

- Advanced CSS and SASS, Udemy, License UC-0abb8933-be1a-4af6-8926-821b5ff14047
- Lean Product Management, Educative Inc., License 487B21tRLDvDV2x3yfNlPK2Vj9OWcG
- Docker and Kubernetes, Udemy, License UC-5e2ea26d-ad7c-4c3b-a6ac-3d9febc74b44
- SQL and PostgreSQL, Udemy, License UC-47a8b993-7f00-4798-9755-43bc2cf6de62
- Accelerated Computer Science Fundamentals Specialization (3 courses), Coursera Online Platform, License 4YUQWFN7UYLJ
- Design Patterns in Modern C++, Udemy, License UC-7Q3ALBMI
- Functional Programming using C++, Udemy, License UC-80E6WWXW
- Beginning Test Driven Development in C++, Udemy, License UC-C9G5N9BL
- Machine Learning, Coursera Online Platform, License VZGG2D4SULCS
- The Complete JavaScript Course, Udemy, License UC-4Y3XWZB2
- The Advanced Web Developer Bootcamp, Udemy, License UC-5V37AUL9
- The Complete React Web Developer Course, Udemy, License UC-MY5S5J1A
- Build Responsive Real World Websites with HTML5 and CSS3, Udemy, License UC-PCEM4OIB

## ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

- Languages: English, Swedish, French, Ukrainian, Russian
- Programming skills:
  - Python: 11 years of experience
  - C/C++: 9 years of experience
  - JavaScript, HTML5, CSS3: 4 years of experience
  - Elixir: 1.5 years of experience
- Technical skills:

- Agile software development
- Business requirements analysis
- Systems design and development
- Embedded systems development
- UI and web development
- Object-oriented and functional programming
- Algorithms and data structures
- Parallel computing (MPI, OpenMP, CUDA)
- TeX/LaTeX typesetting

## **HONORS AND AWARDS**

- 2016 Postdoc professional development travel award, Northwestern University (USA). Won a travel grant to give an invited talk at the International Conference on Quantum Fluids and Solids 2016 (QFS) held in Prague (Czech Republic).
- 2009 CFR research grant, CEA Grenoble (France). As a non-EU citizen, received a research grant which covered the 3-year Ph.D. training at CEA and Université Grenoble Alpes.